Josiah Willard Gibbs Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Josiah Willard Gibbs papers
1811-1947
1863-1903
GEN MSS 1175
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
8.92
(21 boxes)
The collection consists of the papers of Josiah Willard Gibbs (1839-1903), which include correspondence, scientific papers, lecture notes taken by one of Gibbs' students, photographs, scientific illustrations, and honors and awards, as well as correspondence of his father, J. Willard Gibbs (1790-1861).
Gibbs, J. Willard (Josiah Willard), 1839-1903
Josiah Willard Gibbs (1839-1903)
Josiah Willard Gibbs, mathematician and physicist, was born in New Haven on February 11, 1839, the son of Josiah Willard Gibbs, professor of sacred literature at Yale, and Mary Anna Van Cleve. He received a B.A. from Yale in 1858, an M.A. in 1861, and a Ph.D. in 1863. After serving as tutor in Latin (1863-65) and natural philosophy (1865-66), Gibbs went to Europe to study for three years. He returned to New Haven in 1869 and was appointed professor of mathematical physics at Yale in 1871, a position he held until his death.
Best known for developing the theory of thermodynamics, Gibbs wrote a number of extremely important and influential scientific works, the most significant being "Graphical Methods in the Thermodynamics of Fluids" (1873), "A Method of Geometrical Representation of the Thermodynamic Properties of Substances by Means of Surfaces" (1873), "On the Equilibrium of Heterogeneous Substances" (1876, 1878), "Electrochemical Thermodynamics" (1886, 1888), and Elementary Principles in Statistical Mechanics (1902).
He lived at the home of his sister and brother-in-law, Julia Gibbs and Addison Van Name, and died unmarried in New Haven on April 28, 1903.
For additional biographical information, see the Dictionary of American Biography, IV, pp. 248-51; Muriel Rukeyser, Willard Gibbs (1942), and Lynde Phelps Wheeler, Josiah Willard Gibbs, the History of a Great Mind (1951).
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of the papers of Josiah Willard Gibbs (1839-1903), which include correspondence, scientific papers, lecture notes taken by one of Gibbs' students, photographs, scientific illustrations, and honors and awards, as well as correspondence of his father, J. Willard Gibbs (1790-1861). Series I., Josiah Willard Gibbs Correspondence, consists almost entirely of professional and scientific correspondence. Major correspondents include Wilder Dwight Bancroft; Hugo Buchholz; Franklin Bowditch Dexter; Timothy Dwight; Smith B. Goodenow; Wilhelm Ostwald; Karl Planck; and Sir Joseph Thomson. Series II., Notebooks and Scientific Papers, includes documentation of Gibbs' work in vector analysis of orbits; statistical mechanics; and electromechanics. Series III., Class Notes by George P. Starkweather, contains lecture notes taken by Starkweather on subjects including electricity and magnetism; thermodynamics; the electromagnetic theory of light; and vector applications. Series IV., Portraits and Illustrations, contains portraits of J. Willard and of Josiah Willard Gibbs, among other subjects. Series V., Correspondence of J. Willard Gibbs, contains personal and professional correspondence of Josiah Willard Gibbs' father, a theologian and Yale professor. Correspondents include William Henry Beecher; Elijah Coleman Bridgeman; George Edward Day; William Allen Macy; and Benjamin Silliman.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
This collection may be housed off-site at Yale's Library Shelving Facility (LSF). To determine if all or part of this collection is housed off-site please check the library's online catalog, Orbis; material for which the location is given as "LSF" must be requested 36 hours in advance. Please consult with Beinecke Access Services for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Josiah Willard Gibbs Papers are almost entirely the bequest of Addison Van Name, 1922. A few items were donated to Beinecke Library by Theodora Van Name Palmer in 1961.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. Josiah Willard Gibbs Correspondence, 1876-1915; II. Josiah Willard Gibbs Notebooks, Scientific Papers and Personal Papers, 1863-1947; III. Lecture Notes by George P. Starkweather, 1892-1896; IV. Photographs and Illustrations, 1860s; V. Letters by and to J. Willard Gibbs (1790-1861), 1811-1860.
Mathematics -- Study and teaching; Orbits; Physics -- Study and teaching; Physicists -- United States; Scientists -- United States; Physicists -- United States -- 19th century; Scientists -- United States -- 19th century; Bancroft, Wilder D. (Wilder Dwight), 1867-1953; Beecher, William Henry, 1802-1889; Bridgeman, Elijah Coleman; Buchholz, Hugo, 1866-1921; Day, George Edward, 1815-1872; Dexter, Franklin Bowditch, 1842-1920; Dwight, Timothy, 1828-1916; Gibbs family; Gibbs, Josiah W. (Josiah Willard), 1790-1861; Gibbs, J. Willard (Josiah Willard), 1839-1903; Goodenow, Smith B. (Smith Bartlett), 1817-1897; Macy, William Allen; Ostwald, Wilhelm, 1853-1932; Planck, Max, 1858-1947; Silliman, Benjamin, 1779-1864; Starkweather, George P.; Thomson, J. J. (Joseph John), 1856-1940; Yale University
- Josiah Willard Gibbs (1839-1903) Correspondence, 1876-1915; Series I; 1.04; (3 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Organized into three subseries: Letters by Gibbs; Letters to Gibbs, and Collected Correspondence and Related Papers
  - Letters by Gibbs
    - Autograph letter (draft) to Wilder D. Bancroft on the equations of electric motion. [New Haven]., 1899 May; 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Accompanied by a manuscript copy of the letter as sent, in an unidentified hand.
    - 4 autograph letters, signed, and 1 autograph letter (draft) to Carl Barus. New Haven., 1897-1900 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Autograph letter (draft) to George F. Becker. New Haven., 1886 September 13 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Autograph letter, signed, (draft) to [Henry Pickering] Bowditch. [New Haven?], 1891 May 6 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Autograph letter, signed, (draft) to Bernard Brunhes. New Haven., 1902 November 8 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Autograph letter, signed, (draft) to Hugo Bucholz. New Haven., 1898 October (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Autograph letter, signed, (draft) to Henri Louis Le Chatelier. New Haven., 1899 October 28 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Autograph letter, signed, (draft) to Josiah Parsons Cooke. New Haven., 1889 June 10 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Autograph letter, signed, and autograph letter (drafts) to Thomas Craig. New Haven., 1888 July 13 and August 14 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Autograph letter, signed, (draft) to [Pierre Maurice Maire Duhem]. New Haven., 1887 February 2 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Autograph letter, signed, (draft) to Thomas S. Fiske. New Haven., 1891 February 6 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 4 autograph letters, signed, to D. C. Gilman, president of Johns Hopkins University, concerning a projected visit to the university as a lecturer. New Haven., 1879 May 17 and June 5, 1880 March 30 and April 29 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Autograph letter (draft) to B. A. Gould. [New Haven]., 1889 September 23 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Autograph letter, signed, (draft) to Hermann Ernst Grassman. New Haven., 1887 February 2 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Autograph letter (draft) to William Thomson, Lord Kelvin. New Haven., 1902 September 26 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Autograph letter (draft) to [Samuel Pierpont] Langley. New Haven., 1894 May 30 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - 3 autograph letters, signed, (drafts) to Oliver J. Lodge, secretary of the Electrolysis Committee of the British Association for the Advancement of Science. New Haven., 1887 January 8 and November [21], 1888 March 14 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Autograph letter, signed, (draft) to Joseph Lovering. New Haven., 1881 January 5 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Autograph letter (draft) to Alexander McAuley. [New Haven?]., 1892 January 21 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - 5 autograph letters, signed, (drafts) to Wilhelm Ostwald. New Haven., 1887-1891 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Positive photostats of 2 letters and negative photostats of 4 letters to Wilhelm Ostwald, University of Leipzig, Germany. New Haven and Goshen, Massachusetts., 1888-1896 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      Accompanied by a photostat of a page from the Zeitschrift fur Physikalische Chemie, vol. 43 (1903) and a manuscript transcription of the letters made by Fraulein Grete Ostwald.
      Existence and Location of Originals
      The original letters are preserved in the Wilhem Ostwald Archive, Grossbothen, Saxony.
    - Autograph letter (draft) to Charles Santiago Sanders Peirce. New Haven., 1881 December 1 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Autograph letter (draft) to [Victor] Schlegel. [New Haven?], 1888 August 1 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Autograph letter, signed, (draft) to Joseph Ellis Trevor. New Haven., 1899 March 6 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - 3 autograph letters, signed, (drafts) to Messrs. Veit & Comp. New Haven., 1889 January 17, February 16, and March 20 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Letters to Gibbs
    - Abbe, Cleveland - 1 autograph letter, signed, and 3 typed letters, signed to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Washington., 1885 Spetember 28, 1893 May 6, 1902 April 10 and 14 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Abraham, Max (1875-1922) - autograph letter, signed to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Berlin. In German., 1899 November 30 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Aitken, John (1839-1919) - 2 autograph letters, signed to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Selkirk., 1876 December 15, 1877 January 24 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Bakhuis Roozeboom, Hendrik Willem (1854-1907) - Autograph note, signed to [Josiah Willard Gibbs]. Amsterdam., 1902 April 3 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Ball, Sir Robert Stawell (1840-1913) - Typed letter, signed to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Cambridge, England., 1902 March 29 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Bancroft, Wilder Dwight (1867- ) - 5 autograph letters, signed to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Ithaca, New York., 1898 January 13, 1899 March 18 and May 20 and June 4 and July 4 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Barth, Johannes A. - Copy of an autograph letter, signed, to Scribners., 1902 July 10 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Baynes, Robert Edward (1849-1921) - Autograph letter, signed to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Oxford., 1879 January 27 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Becker, George Ferdinand (1847-1919) - Autograph letter, signed to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Newport, Rhode Island., 1886 August 18 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Bentze, Frederick - Copy of an autograph letter, signed, written in Gibbs' hand, to Josiah Willard Gibbs, concerning the translation of Vector Analysis into German. Austria., 1903 January 3 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Besant, William Henry (1828-1917) - Autograph letter, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Cambridge, England., 1885 August 8 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Boltzmann, Ludwig (1844-1906) - Letter, signed, partially in autograph, to [Josiah Willard Gibbs]. Munchen., 1892 May 12 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Bosscha, Johannes (1831-1911) - Autograph letter, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Haarlem., 1902 April 3 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Bowditch, Henry Pickering (1840-1911) - 2 autograph letters, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Boston., 1891 May 3 and May 9 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Brunhes, Bernard - 2 autograph letters, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. France., 1902 October 26 and November 14 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Bucherer, Alfred Heinrich - Autograph letter, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Bonn., 1902 January 30 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Buchholz, Hugo (1866- ) - 2 autograph letters, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Jena and Gottingen., 1898 August 1 and September 16 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Buchholz, Hugo (1895- ) - 2 autograph letters, signed, and 1 postcard to Ralph Gibbs Van Name, concerning the publication of The Scientific Papers of J. Willard Gibbs. Halle and Jena., 1906 December 8, 13 and 28 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Bumstead, Henry Andrews (1870-1920) - Typed letter, signed, to Edwin Bidwell Wilson, regarding Gibbs' interest in statistical mechanics. New Haven., 1915 December 22 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Burbury, Samuel Hawksley (1830-1911) - 8 autograph letters, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. London., 1902-1903 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Byerly, William Elwood (1849-1935) - Autograph letter, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Cambridge, Massachusetts., 1881 November 26 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Chamberlain, Joshua Lawrence (1828-1914) - Autograph letter, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Brunswick, Maine., 1873 November 12 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Chambers, Charles (1834-1896) - Autograph letter, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Bombay., 1880 January 31 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Le Chatelier, Henri Louis (1850-1936) - Typed letter, signed, to [Josiah Willard Gibbs]. Paris., 1902 April 29 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Le Chatelier, Henri Louis (1850-1936) - Typed letter, signed, to Ralph Gibbs Van Name, concerning the publication of The Scientific Papers of J. Willard Gibbs. Paris., 1907 January 31 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Cooke, Josiah Parsons (1827-1894) - 2 autograph letters, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Cambridge, Massachusetts., 1889 June 5 and 13 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Couturat, Louis (1868-1914) - Autograph letter, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Paris., 1899 November 30 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Craig, Thomas (1855-1900) - 3 autograph letters, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Baltimore., 1882 May 24, 1883 April 26, 1888 August 6 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Dana, James Dwight (1813-1895) - Autograph letter, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. New Haven., 1880 April 26 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Darwin, Sir George Howard (1845-1912) - Autograph letter, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Cambridge., 1902 April 18 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Dewar, Sir James (1842-1923) - Autograph letter, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Cambridge., 1883 March 23 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Dexter, Franklin Bowditch (1842-1920) - 3 autograph letters, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs, concerning his salary as professor at Yale. New Haven., 1880 April 28 and June 29, 1893 November 15 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Duhem, Pierre Maurice Maire (1861-1916) - 4 autograph letters, signed, to [Josiah Willard Gibbs]. Paris., 1887 January 10 and February 16, 1900 May 29, 1902 April 9 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Dwight, Timothy (1828-1916) - 2 autograph letters, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs, concerning his salary as professor at Yale. New Haven., 1893 November 15, 1896 January 25 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Eddy, Henry Turner (1844- ) - Autograph letter, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Cincinnati., 1883 March 13 (Box 2, Folder 60)
      Enclosed is a reprint of Eddy's paper, "Radiant heat an exception to the second law of thermodynamics."
    - Engel, Friedrich (1861- ) - Autograph letter, signed, to [Josiah Willard Gibbs]. Leipzig., 1893 January 8 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Engelmann, Wilhelm (1808-1878) - 2 autograph letters, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Leipzig., 1892 March 10, 1895 December 23 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Foppl, A. - Autograph letter, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Munchen., 1902 January 6 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Freeman, Alexander - 8 autograph letters, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs., 1875-1890 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Gibbs, Wolcott (1822-1908) - 3 autograph letters, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Newport, [Rhode Island?]., 1881 December 4, 1897 June 15, 1902 April 19 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Gilman, Daniel Coit (1831-1908) - 4 autograph letters, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Baltimore., 1879 May 13, 29, and June 13, 1880 April 8 (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Glazebrook, R. T. - Invitation to a meeting of the British Association for the Advancement of Science, to J. Willard Gibbs, with a manuscript note., 1893 June 5 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - Goodenow, Smith B. - 18 autograph letters, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs, concerning a theory of Goodenow's on the velocity of sound. Battle Creek, Iowa., 1888-1889 (Box 2, Folder 68)
      Accompanied by 2 drafts of Gibbs' reply to the letter of 1888 July 4.
    - Gould, Alice Bache - Autograph letter, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. [Chicago]., 1897 March 15 (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - Gould, Benjamin Apthorp, Jr. (1824-1896) - Autograph letter, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Cambridge, [Massachusetts]., 1889 October 16 (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - Grassman, Hermann Ernst (1857- ) - 2 autograph letters, signed, and 3 autograph postcards, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Halle., 1888-1893 (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - Griffiths, Ernest Howard (1851-1932) - Autograph letter, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Cambridge, [England]., 1895 December 18 (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - Hagen, John George (1847- ) - 2 autograph letters, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Washington., 1893 March 16 and June 20 (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - Hall, Asaph (1829-1907) - Autograph letter, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs., 1886 September 2 (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - Heaviside, Oliver (1850-1925) - 2 autograph letters, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. London and Paignton, Devon., 1888 July 3, 1894 April 6 (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - Herman et Cie (publishers) - Postcard to Josiah Willard Gibbs concerning a reprint of his "On the equilibrium of heterogeneous substances." Paris., 1898 February 6 (Box 2, Folder 76)
      Accompanied by a draft of Gibbs' reply, 1898 March 10.
    - Herman et Cie (publishers) - Typed letter, signed, to [Addison?] Van Name, concerning a reprint of J. Willard Gibbs' Statistical Mechanics. Paris., 1912 November 18 (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - Hertz, Heinrich Rudolph (1857-1894) - Autograph letter, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs., 1889 March 3 (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - Hill, Thomas (1818-1891) - 2 autograph letters, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Portland, Maine., 1890 Janaury 7 and February 17 (Box 2, Folder 79)
    - Kamerlingh Onnes, Heike (1853-1926) - 2 autograph letters, signed, to [Josiah Willard] Gibbs. Leiden., 1900 May 8, 1901 June 19 (Box 2, Folder 80)
    - Kelvin, William Thomson, 1st baron (1824-1907) - 2 autograph letters, signed, and 1 typed letter, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. [London] and Ayrshire., 1901 July 29, 1902 April 11 and October 14 (Box 2, Folder 81)
    - Klein, Felix (1849-1925) - 3 autograph letters, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Gottingen and Evanston, Illinois., 1892 September 22, 1893 September 17, 1895 June 27 (Box 2, Folder 82)
    - Knott, Cargill Gilston (1856-1922) - Autograph letter, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Edinburgh., 1893 April 26 (Box 2, Folder 83)
    - Kronecker, Leopold (1823-1891) - Autograph letter, signed, to [Josiah Willard Gibbs]. Berlin., 1891 June 2 (Box 2, Folder 84)
    - Langley, Samuel Pierpont (1834-1906) - 1 autograph letter, signed, and 3 typed letters, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Allegheny, Pennsylvania and Washington., 1886 June 9, 1894 April 13 and June 9, 1895 January 25 (Box 3, Folder 85)
    - Lodge, Sir Oliver Joseph (1851-1940) - Autograph postcard, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Liverpool., 1887 January 20 (Box 3, Folder 86)
    - Lorentz, Hendrik Antoon (1853-1928) - Autograph postcard, signed, and autograph letter, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Leiden., 1884 April 8, 1902 April 1 (Box 3, Folder 87)
    - Loverling, Joseph (1813-1892) - Autograph letter, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Cambridge, [Massachusetts]., 1881 December 31 (Box 3, Folder 88)
    - Macfarlane, Alexander (1851-1913) - 3 autograph letters, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. South Bethlehem, Pennsylvania; Chatham, Ontario., 1899 February 22, 1901 June 18 and July 12 (Box 3, Folder 89)
    - Massieu, Francois Jacques Dominique (1832-1896) - Autograph letter, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Rennes., 1878 October 9 (Box 3, Folder 90)
    - McAulay, Alexander (1863-1931) - Autograph letter, signed, to Oliver Heaviside. Hobart, Tasmania., 1894 February 18 (Box 3, Folder 91)
    - Meldola, Raphael (1849-1915) - Autograph letter, signed, to [Josiah Willard Gibbs]. Toronto., 1897 August 23 (Box 3, Folder 92)
    - Mellor, Joseph William (1873-1938) - Autograph letter, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Newcastle-under-Lyme, Staffordshire., 1902 September 17 (Box 3, Folder 93)
    - Meyerhoffer, Wilhelm (1864- ) - Autograph letter, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Wien., 1893 June 23 (Box 3, Folder 94)
    - Michelson, Albert Abraham (1852-1931) - 6 autograph letters, signed, to [Josiah Willard] Gibbs. Cleveland., 1884-1890 (Box 3, Folder 95)
    - Moore, Eliakim Hastings (1862-1932) - Autograph letter, signed, and typed letter, signed, to [Josiah Willard] Gibbs. Evanston, Illinois and [Chicago]., 1890 January 27, 1902 June 21 (Box 3, Folder 96)
    - Muir, M. M. Pattison - Autograph letter, signed, to J. Willard Gibbs. Cambridge, [England]., 1880 February 14 (Box 3, Folder 97)
    - Newcomb, Simon (1835-1909) - 2 autograph letters, signed, to [Josiah Willard] Gibbs. Washington., 1901 November 22, 1902 March 15 (Box 3, Folder 98)
    - Newton, Hubert Anson (1830-1896) - Autograph letter, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Florence., 1880 May 31 (Box 3, Folder 99)
    - Ostwald, Wilhelm (1853-1932) - 11 autograph letters, signed, and 1 autograph postcard, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Riga, Russland, and Leipzig., 1887-1895 (Box 3, Folder 100)
    - Peirce, Charles Santiago Sanders (1839-1914) - Autograph letter, signed, to [Josiah Willard Gibbs]. Baltimore., 1881 [November 20] (Box 3, Folder 101)
    - Pierce, J. M. - Autograph letter, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Cambridge, Massachusetts., 1884 March 10 (Box 3, Folder 102)
    - Pirie, George (1843-1904) - 2 autograph letters, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Cambridge, England., 1878 January 16 and April 10 (Box 3, Folder 103)
    - Planck, Karl Ernst Ludwig (1858-1947) - Autograph letter, signed, to [Josiah Willard Gibbs]. Berlin., 1902 March 29 (Box 3, Folder 104)
    - Poincare, Henri (1854-1912) - Autograph note, signed, to [Josiah Willard Gibbs]. Paris., 1901 April 29 (Box 3, Folder 105)
    - Ramsay, William - 3 autograph letters, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Bristol, London., [1884?], 1885 March 5, 1897 June 17 (Box 3, Folder 106)
    - Rayleigh, Lord - 3 autograph letters, signed, one with typescript, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Essex., 1892 June 5, [1901], 1902 March 3 (Box 3, Folder 107)
    - Rood, Ogden Nicholas (1831-1902) - Autograph letter, signed, to [Josiah Willard] Gibbs. New York., 1893 October 8 (Box 3, Folder 108)
    - Rowland, Henry Augustus (1848-1901) - 2 autograph letters, signed, and 1 letter, signed, to [Josiah Willard] Gibbs. Baltimore., 1879 March 3 and May 28, [1884?] July 29 (Box 3, Folder 109)
    - Schlegel, Victor (1843-1908) - 2 autograph letters, signed, to [Josiah Willard Gibbs]. Hagen., 1888 July 15, 1891 August 16 (Box 3, Folder 110)
    - Stallo, John Bernard (1823-1900) - Autograph letter, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Cincinnati., 1884 July 30 (Box 3, Folder 111)
    - Study, E. - Autograph letter, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Marburg., 1889 July 30 (Box 3, Folder 112)
    - Sylvester, James Joseph (1814-1897) - 2 autograph letters, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Baltimore., 1883 April 12, 1886 November 18 (Box 3, Folder 113)
    - Taft, William H. - Autograph letter, signed, to H. A. Newton. Cincinnati., 1884 July 18 (Box 3, Folder 114)
    - Thomson, Sir Joseph John (1856-1940) - 5 autograph letters, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Cambridge, [England]., 1884-1902, no date (Box 3, Folder 115)
    - Todhunter, Isaac (1820-1884) - Autograph letter, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Cambridge., 1879 July 7 (Box 3, Folder 116)
    - Trevor, Joseph Ellis (1864-1941) - 5 autograph letters, signed, and 2 typed letters, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Ithaca., 1895-1899 (Box 3, Folder 117)
    - Trobridge, John - 3 autograph letters, signed, to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Cambridge., 1880 June 9, 1881 January 5 and 13 (Box 3, Folder 118)
    - Veit & Comp (publishers) - 2 letters to Josiah Willard Gibbs. Leipzig., 1888 December 30, 1889 May 5 (Box 3, Folder 119)